Finding Aid for George Henry Cannon papers, 1833-1915
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Henry Cannon papers 1833-1915
Cannon, George Henry, b. 1826.
1 microfilms
1 linear feet
8592 Aa 2; AA microcopy
Surveyor of lands in northern Michigan and in the Upper Peninsula; Macomb County land speculator; journal of his surveying expedition along the shores of Lake Superior, letters received, historical essays, family materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Leah Atwater (donor no. 6278 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George Cannon was born on December 30, 1826, in Day, New York, to Pearl and Mary Cannon. In 1833, the family moved to Michigan, first to Saline, in Washtenaw County, and then to Bruce, in Macomb County. As a young man, Cannon worked mornings and nights for his board, and, at the end of school-terms, for his teachers, to pay tuition. During the summer of 1846, he was part of an exploring party searching for minerals (primarily copper) in the Lake Superior region of the Upper Peninsula. In the summer of 1847 he explored the Ontonagon Range. After he returned from the Upper Peninsula in 1847, he attended the Academy at Rochester, in Oakland County, for two years, after which he spent four years teaching in the area.
Cannon had developed an interest in exploration, and especially surveying while in the mineral region, and it continued throughout his life. In the spring of 1849, he was employed by Judge W.A. Burt, who had been Dr. Douglass Houghton's assistant, and later took over the task of completing Houghton's survey of the State. During 1849, Cannon surveyed the sub-divisional lines of ten townships. In August of 1849, he was appointed U.S. Deputy Surveyor, and completed nine contracts in that capacity, including the Grand Traverse region, many towns in the Cheboygan area, and the islands of Saginaw Bay. He also worked in the Upper Peninsula, and was appointed to examine the surveys in the relatively unexplored territory between Lakes Superior and Michigan, and the area between the Pictured Rocks and the meridian line. He also surveyed the township lines on the north shore of Lake Superior, near Pigeon River, in Minnesota. In 1852, he made surveys in the Grand Traverse region between Higgins Lake and Elk Rapids. During the winter of 1852-53 he surveyed the islands of Saginaw Bay. He then began a survey of public lands of the Upper Peninsula from the meridian at the "Soo" to the west for 108 miles.
His final survey, in 1856, was the laying out of an extensive Indian reservation in Minnesota. Public survey work was discontinued the following year, and Cannon began his work examining and selecting pine and farmlands in Michigan and Wisconsin. He resided in Macomb County in the city of Washington, and held extensive lands in several areas of the State.
In the 1890s, Cannon was active in both the Macomb County Historical Society and the Michigan Pioneer and Historical Society. One of his interests was the history of the disputed boundary line between Michigan and Wisconsin because of a surveying error.
The George Cannon collection consists of letters, a journal, historical essays written for the Macomb County Historical Society, and various land records, including some surveying notes. Most of the letters were received by Cannon or other members of his family. There is in these letters much documentation relating to the Upper Peninsula and to the history of the settlement of Macomb County. Of especial interest are those letters and documents relating to the border dispute between Wisconsin and Michigan (particularly in the period of the first decade of the 20th Century) arising out of a surveying error in the 1830s. Many of the letters are from Upper Peninsula businessman and University of Michigan Regent Peter White.
Other items of interest are essays and lectures of the students who attended the Stony Creek Lyceum Rochester School where Cannon taught in the 1840s, a few Civil War letters from his brother Levi Cannon who served with Co. B of the 22nd Michigan Infantry, and essays Cannon wrote on his surveying mentor William A. Burt and on the early settlement of Macomb County.
Subjects:
Burt, William Austin, 1792-1858.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Macomb County (Mich.)--History.; Michigan--Boundaries--Wisconsin.; Wisconsin--Boundaries--Michigan.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Superior, Lake.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Surveyors--Michigan.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 22nd (1862-1865). Company B.
Contributors:
Cannon, Levi H., b. 1830 or 31.; Crapo, Henry Howland, 1830-1920.; White, Peter, 1830-1908.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Journal
  - Account of surveying expedition of the Lake Superior shoreline 1846, 1 microfilms (Reel 1)
    (The journal was entitled, "A Narrative of one year in the Wilderness," including discussion of Upper Peninsula settlements, rivers, landmarks, and Indians.)
  - Published transcript of "A Narrative of one year in the Wilderness" 1982 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and other papers
  - Biographical sketch of George H. Cannon (written for Historical and Pioneer Society of Michigan) (Box 1)
  - GHC's notebook: surveying notes; estimates of value of hardwoods in Michigan and Ontario (Box 1)
  - Warranty deed 1833 (Box 1)
  - Letters received 1836, 1846-1849 (Box 1)
  - Essays and addresses of members of the Stony Creek Lyceum Rochester School circa 1845-1852 (Box 1)
  - Essays, lectures, miscellaneous 1840s (Box 1)
  - Manuscript literary journal entitled "The Students Repository" edited by George H. Cannon 1848 (Box 1)
  - Letters received and other materials 1850s, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters received 1860s (Box 1)
    (include letters from Henry H. Crapo, June 30, 1866, and from brother Levi Cannon while serving with Co. B, 22nd Michigan Infantry during the Civil War)
  - Survey records entitled "Meanders on Lake Superior Reservation from point on Rock thence along the Shore" (Box 1)
  - Letters received 1870s (Box 1)
  - Letters received 1880s, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters received 1890s (Box 1)
  - Letters received 1901-1915 (Box 1)
  - William A. Burt
    - Newspaper article and government document about (Box 1)
    - Essay: "The Death of Hon. William A. Burt" [August 1858]; also notebook containing GHC's memories of Burt and research about him (Box 1)
  - Macomb County Historical Society (document addressed to the Society) (Box 1)
  - Essay: "Incident in the Life of One Pioneer" probably read before the Macomb County Historical Society and recounting the memories of an early settler (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical essay written about Nathaniel Carter, early Macomb County settler (Box 1)
  - Meeting of early pioneers of Macomb County May 26, 1881 (Box 1)
  - Michigan-Wisconsin boundary dispute
    - Letters 1903-1908 (Box 1)
      (include numerous letters from Peter White)
    - Other documents (Box 1)
  - Macomb County Historical Society / Historical and Pioneer Society of Michigan: letters, programs, essays, etc. (Box 1)
  - Postal cards with brief messages (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: warranty deed, land contract (Box 1)
  - Photoprint of George and Lucy Cannon 1870s (Box 1)